迁徙的鸟
灰雁飞越1800英里
The graylag goose flies 1800 miles...
从欧洲西南部到斯堪的那维亚半岛
...from south-western Europe to Scandinavia.
候鸟的故事是一个关于承诺的故事
The story of migrating birds is the story of a promise:
一个对归来的承诺
The promise to return.
它们的旅程千里迢迢  历经了危机重重
They fly, often thousands of miles, beset with danger...
只为一个目的
...for a single reason:
生存
To survive.
候鸟的迁徙是为生命而战
Their migration is a fight for life.
春天来临时  它们振翅飞向北极的故土
When spring comes, they take wing for the Arctic.
有些一鼓作气  不舍昼夜
Some fly relentlessly, night and day.
另一些则且行且驻
Others make the trip in stages...
艰难地向着遥远的目的地挺进
...laboring to reach their distant destination.
欧亚灰鹤飞越2500英里  自西班牙至北方针叶林
The Eurasian crane flies 2500 miles from Spain to the boreal forest.
白鹳飞越3100英里  自非洲中部至欧洲西部
The white stork flies 3100 miles from central Africa to western Europe.
为了从一个纬度向另一个纬度的行进中不迷失方向
To navigate across the latitudes...
候鸟借助了天文标记
...they use the natural beacons of the universe
太阳和星辰
The sun, the stars.
它们对地球磁场也十分敏感
They can track the earth's magnetic field...
如同使用了指南针
...as sensitively as a compass needle.
白额黑雁飞越1500英里  自欧洲西部至格棱兰岛
The barnacle goose flies 1500 miles from western Europe to Greenland.
大天鹅飞越1800英里
The whooper swan flies 1800 miles...
自远东至西伯利亚冰原
...from the Far East to the Siberian tundra.
北半球的各处
All over the Northern Hemisphere...
所有的大陆上  春季的迁徙已经开始
...on every continent the spring migration has begun.
没有什么能够阻挡
No barriers stop them.
鸟儿一路向北
The birds make straight for the far north.
斑头雁飞越1500英里  自印度至中亚草原
The bar-headed goose flies 1500 miles from India to the central Asia steppes.
丹顶鹤飞越600英里  自远东至西伯利亚针叶林
The red-crowned crane flies 600 miles from the Far East to the Siberian taiga.
白头鹰飞越1800英里  自美国西部至阿拉斯加
The bald eagle flies 1800 miles from the American West to Alaska.
加拿大雁飞越2000英里
The Canada goose flies 2000 miles...
自墨西哥湾至北极圈
...from the Gulf of Mexico to the Arctic Circle.
穿越美洲
All across America...
从海岸到另一侧的海岸
...from coast to coast...
候鸟向北极圈振翼前行
...the migrants wing their way towards the Arctic Circle.
雪雁飞越2500英里  自墨西哥湾至北极地区
The snow goose flies 2500 miles from the Gulf of Mexico to the Arctic lands.
俄勒冈州的克拉克水鸟
The Clark's grebe in Oregon.
沙丘鹤飞越2000英里
The sandhill crane flies 2000 miles...
自美国中部平原至北极地区
...from the central American plains to the Arctic lands.
爱德华州的大松鸡
The greater sage grouse in Idaho.
来自各个大陆的侯鸟
Coming from every continent...
终于在北极会合  旋即分离
...the migrant birds converge upon the Arctic and disperse.
群居的生活已经结束
Their life as a community is over.
现在  是享受天伦之乐的时候了
Now, it's family time.
海角天涯  有另一个世界
There is a world apart:
海鸟的国度
The realm of sea birds.
每年春天  他们远离碧波
Every spring, they quit the ocean waves...
成群结队的在峭壁岩礁上筑巢
...and flock to nest on the same cliffs and rocks.
海鸠散布在北大西洋
The common murre are scattered over the North Atlantic.
北大西洋中的北鲣鸟
The northern gannet in the North Atlantic.
大西洋的夏季转瞬即逝
The Arctic summer is short-lived.
很快  北国疆土就会被极夜的寒冷所吞没
Soon the northern lands will be locked in the cold of the polar night.
秋季的迁徙开始了
It is time for the fall migration.
食物匮乏  该离开了
No more food. Time to leave.
南飞的迁行攸关生死
Flying south is now a matter of life or death.
北极燕飞越12500英里  自北极至南极
The Arctic tern flies 12,500 miles from the Arctic to the Antarctic.
辽阔的大洋上
Out in the ocean...
任何浮物都能让疲累的鸟儿憩息
...any floating refuge can save the life of an exhausted bird.
除此之外  一路无法停歇
For the others, there's no rest until the coast.
秋天  面临的主要问题是如何
In the fall, there is one prime necessity:
避开恶劣的天气
Stay clear of bad weather.
穿越北美继续南行
Traveling south through North America.
红胸黑雁　向南飞越东欧
The red-breasted goose traveling south through eastern Europe.
秋天的迁徙会让队伍减员
The fall migration thins the ranks.
而幸存者中  跟随成年候鸟并肩而飞的幼鸟
Among the survivors, by flying with their elders...
会记住路线  熟识地表
...the youngsters memorize the route and recognize the landmarks...
他们一年迁行两次  终生如此
...they will fly over twice a year, throughout their lives.
飞至非洲
Traveling into Africa.
对于飞离北欧的数百万只鸟儿而言
For millions of birds from Europe...
它们迁徙的终点将是非洲
...the journey's end is Africa...
很多鸟儿无法完成这段旅程
...but many will fall by the wayside.
涉禽类飞越6200英里  自北极圈至非洲西海岸
The waders fly 6200 miles from the Arctic Circle to the west coast of Africa.
在这场伟大旅程的终点  热带
At the end of their odyssey...
各地的鸟儿如蒙天堂
...birds from all over reach the heavenly tropics.
非洲白鹈鹕穿越非洲
The African white pelican crossing Africa.
天堂般的生活转瞬即逝
Heaven is ephemeral.
只持续了短短一个季节
It will only last a season.
再一次的
Once again...
它们冲入天空  为食物和生存进行无尽的搜寻
...they must take to the skies in their endless search for food.
亚马逊河
The Amazon.
南极洲周围的信天翁
The albatross around Antarctica.
没有哪块大陆能够阻挡南海的怒涛
No landmass slows the swell of the southern oceans.
但海鸟却能在狂风席卷的小岛上筑巢安家
Sea birds nest on wind-lashed islands.
年轻的信天翁常年盘旋于南极大陆之上
The young albatross only comes to land...
只是偶作停留
...after circling the Antarctic for several years.
凤冠企鹅迁行620英里
The rockhopper penguin travels 620 miles...
追随南大西洋环流
...following South Atlantic currents.
帝企鹅的迁徙
The king penguin travels...
自南部大陆至南极洲群岛
...from the southern continents to the Antarctic islands.
一年过去
A year has passed.
无数鸟儿飞越了千万里
Millions of birds have flown thousands of miles.
天空中  年复一年的旅程再次开始
In the sky, the same journeys start over again.
在北半球
In the Northern Hemisphere...
候鸟们带来了春的气息
...migrating birds herald a new spring.
归来的承诺得以兑现
The promise to return has been fulfilled.
飘过洋跨过海
Across the oceans Across the seas
越过黝黑的丛林
Over forests of blackened trees
穿过山谷仍不停歇
Through valleys so still we dare not breathe
只为来到你身旁
To be by your side
越过变幻的平原
Over the shifting desert plains
穿过金黄色的山脉
Across mountains all in flames
顶着狂风冒着暴雨
Through howling winds and driving rains
只为来到你身旁
To be by your side
一年年的一里里路
Every mile and every year
撒下的一滴滴泪
for every one a little tear
亲爱的  万语千言我无法诉说
I cannot explain this, Dear
只为信守诺言
I will not even try
投入群星璀璨的夜空
Into the night as the stars collide
越过那些冰冷的山石
Across the borders that divide
和森林分界的边境
forests of stone standing petrified
只为来到你身旁
To be by your side
一年年的一里里路
Every mile and every year
撒下的一滴滴泪
For every one a single tear
亲爱的  万语千言我无法诉说
I cannot explain this, Dear
只为信守诺言
I will not even try
因为我坚信
For I know one thing
是爱让我们飞翔
Love comes on a wing
今夜我会来到你身旁
For tonight I will be by your side
而明天我依旧会飞翔
But tomorrow I will fly
从汪洋到高山
From the deepest ocean To the highest peak
越过你沉睡着的疆土
Through the frontiers of your sleep
穿越无名的山谷
Into the valley where we dare not speak
只为来到你身旁
To be by your side
越过无边的荒野
Across the endless wilderness
所有的野兽向我鞠躬
where all the beasts bow down their heads
亲爱的  我不能停歇
Darling I will never rest
直到飞到你身旁
till I am by your side
一年年的一里里路
Every mile and every year
时空变换消失不见
Time and Distance disappear
亲爱的  万语千言我无法诉说
I cannot explain this, Dear
只为信守诺言
No, I will not even try
而我坚信
And I know just one thing
是爱让我们飞翔
Love comes on a wing
今夜我会来到你身旁
and tonight I will be by your side
而明天我即将离去
But tomorrow I will fly away
爱随太阳一同升起
Love rises with the day
也许今夜我就能来到你身旁
and tonight I may be by your side
而明天我依旧会飞翔
But tomorrow I will fly
明天我依旧会飞翔
Tomorrow I will fly